<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://software-ethics-casebook.github.io//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://software-ethics-casebook.github.io//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-04-12T18:10:45+02:00</updated><id>https://software-ethics-casebook.github.io//</id><title type="html">The Software Ethics Casebook</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Googlers letter against warfare technology</title><link href="https://software-ethics-casebook.github.io//googlers-letter-against-warfare-technology" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Googlers letter against warfare technology" /><published>2018-04-12T13:30:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-04-12T13:30:00+02:00</updated><id>https://software-ethics-casebook.github.io//googlers-letter-against-warfare-technology</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://software-ethics-casebook.github.io//googlers-letter-against-warfare-technology">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Dear Sundar,
&lt;strong&gt;We believe that Google should not be in the business of war. Therefore we ask that Project Maven be cancelled, and that Google draft, publicize and
enforce a clear policy stating that neither Google nor its contractors will
ever build warfare technology.&lt;/strong&gt;
[…]
We cannot &lt;strong&gt;outsource the moral responsibility of our technologies to third parties&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;source&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://static01.nyt.com/files/2018/technology/googleletter.pdf&quot;&gt;https://static01.nyt.com/files/2018/technology/googleletter.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gizmodo.com/google-is-helping-the-pentagon-build-ai-for-drones-1823464533&quot;&gt;https://gizmodo.com/google-is-helping-the-pentagon-build-ai-for-drones-1823464533&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/04/04/technology/google-letter-ceo-pentagon-project.html&quot;&gt;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/04/04/technology/google-letter-ceo-pentagon-project.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="case" /><category term="position" /><category term="warfare" /><summary type="html">Dear Sundar, We believe that Google should not be in the business of war. Therefore we ask that Project Maven be cancelled, and that Google draft, publicize and enforce a clear policy stating that neither Google nor its contractors will ever build warfare technology. […] We cannot outsource the moral responsibility of our technologies to third parties</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Open Letter from US Researchers in Cryptography and Information Security</title><link href="https://software-ethics-casebook.github.io//an-open-letter-from-us-researchers-in-cryptography-and-information-security" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Open Letter from US Researchers in Cryptography and Information Security" /><published>2018-04-06T19:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-04-06T19:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://software-ethics-casebook.github.io//an-open-letter-from-us-researchers-in-cryptography-and-information-security</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://software-ethics-casebook.github.io//an-open-letter-from-us-researchers-in-cryptography-and-information-security">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Media reports since last June have revealed that the US government conducts domestic and international surveillance on a massive scale, that it engages in deliberate and covert weakening of Internet security standards, and that it pressures US technology companies to deploy backdoors and other data-collection features. As leading members of the US cryptography and information-security research communities, we deplore these practices and urge that they be changed. […]
The choice is not whether to allow the NSA to spy. The choice is between a communications infrastructure that is vulnerable to attack at its core and one that, by default, is intrinsically secure for its users. Every country, including our own, must give intelligence and law-enforcement authorities the means to pursue terrorists and criminals, but we can do so without fundamentally undermining the security that enables commerce, entertainment, personal communication, and other aspects of 21st-century life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;source&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://masssurveillance.info/&quot;&gt;http://masssurveillance.info/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="position" /><category term="mass surveillance" /><summary type="html">Media reports since last June have revealed that the US government conducts domestic and international surveillance on a massive scale, that it engages in deliberate and covert weakening of Internet security standards, and that it pressures US technology companies to deploy backdoors and other data-collection features. As leading members of the US cryptography and information-security research communities, we deplore these practices and urge that they be changed. […] The choice is not whether to allow the NSA to spy. The choice is between a communications infrastructure that is vulnerable to attack at its core and one that, by default, is intrinsically secure for its users. Every country, including our own, must give intelligence and law-enforcement authorities the means to pursue terrorists and criminals, but we can do so without fundamentally undermining the security that enables commerce, entertainment, personal communication, and other aspects of 21st-century life.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is it unethical for me to not tell my employer I’ve automated my job?</title><link href="https://software-ethics-casebook.github.io//is-it-unethical-for-me-to-not-tell-my-employer-ive-automated-my-job" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is it unethical for me to not tell my employer I’ve automated my job?" /><published>2018-04-06T00:30:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-04-06T00:30:00+02:00</updated><id>https://software-ethics-casebook.github.io//is-it-unethical-for-me-to-not-tell-my-employer-ive-automated-my-job</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://software-ethics-casebook.github.io//is-it-unethical-for-me-to-not-tell-my-employer-ive-automated-my-job">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As you can guess, it is pretty much the most boring job ever. However, it’s a full time job with decent pay, and I work remotely so I can stay home with my son.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;So I’ve been doing it for about 18 months and in that time, I’ve basically figured out all the traps to the point where I’ve actually written a program which for the past 6 months has been just doing the whole thing for me. […]&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Now the problem is, do I tell them? If I tell them, they will probably just take the program and get rid of me. This isn’t like a company with tons of IT work - they have a legacy system where they keep all their customer data since forever, and they just need someone to maintain it. At the same time, it doesn’t feel like I’m doing the right thing. I mean, right now, once I get the specs, I run it through my program - then every week or so, I tell them I’ve completed some part of it and get them to test it. I even insert a few bugs here and there to make it look like it’s been generated by a human.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;There might be amendments to the spec and corresponding though email etc, but overall, I spend probably 1-2 hours per week on my job for which I am getting a full time wage.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I really enjoy the free time but would it be unethical to continue with this arrangement without mentioning anything? It’s not like I’m cheating the company. The company has never indicated they’re dissatisfied with my performance and in fact, are getting exactly what they want from employing me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;discussion&quot;&gt;Discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Software developers differed widely in the ensuing discussion. Some suggested this was an outright fraud, other suggested that the right course of action was to reveal to the employer just that the system could be automated, and negotiate on that basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;source&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://workplace.stackexchange.com/questions/93696/is-it-unethical-for-me-to-not-tell-my-employer-i-ve-automated-my-job&quot;&gt;https://workplace.stackexchange.com/questions/93696/is-it-unethical-for-me-to-not-tell-my-employer-i-ve-automated-my-job&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="case" /><category term="technological unemployment" /><summary type="html">As you can guess, it is pretty much the most boring job ever. However, it’s a full time job with decent pay, and I work remotely so I can stay home with my son. So I’ve been doing it for about 18 months and in that time, I’ve basically figured out all the traps to the point where I’ve actually written a program which for the past 6 months has been just doing the whole thing for me. […] Now the problem is, do I tell them? If I tell them, they will probably just take the program and get rid of me. This isn’t like a company with tons of IT work - they have a legacy system where they keep all their customer data since forever, and they just need someone to maintain it. At the same time, it doesn’t feel like I’m doing the right thing. I mean, right now, once I get the specs, I run it through my program - then every week or so, I tell them I’ve completed some part of it and get them to test it. I even insert a few bugs here and there to make it look like it’s been generated by a human. There might be amendments to the spec and corresponding though email etc, but overall, I spend probably 1-2 hours per week on my job for which I am getting a full time wage. I really enjoy the free time but would it be unethical to continue with this arrangement without mentioning anything? It’s not like I’m cheating the company. The company has never indicated they’re dissatisfied with my performance and in fact, are getting exactly what they want from employing me.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">IETF Considers “Mitigation of Pervasive Monitoring” an “Internet Best Current Practice”</title><link href="https://software-ethics-casebook.github.io//ietf-considers-mitigation-of-pervasive-monitoring-to-be-an-internet-best-current-practice" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="IETF Considers &quot;Mitigation of Pervasive Monitoring&quot; an &quot;Internet Best Current Practice&quot;" /><published>2018-04-06T00:30:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-04-06T00:30:00+02:00</updated><id>https://software-ethics-casebook.github.io//ietf-considers-mitigation-of-pervasive-monitoring-to-be-an-internet-best-current-practice</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://software-ethics-casebook.github.io//ietf-considers-mitigation-of-pervasive-monitoring-to-be-an-internet-best-current-practice">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Pervasive Monitoring (PM) is widespread (and often covert) surveillance through intrusive gathering of protocol artefacts, including application content, or protocol metadata such as headers. Active or passive wiretaps and traffic analysis, (e.g., correlation, timing or measuring packet sizes), or subverting the cryptographic keys used to secure protocols can also be used as part of pervasivemonitoring. PM is distinguished by being indiscriminate and very large scale, rather than by introducing new types of technical compromise.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The IETF community’s technical assessment is that PM is an attack on the privacy of Internet users and organisations. The IETF community has expressed strong agreement that PM is an attack that needs to bemitigated where possible, via the design of protocols that make PM significantly more expensive or infeasible.[…]&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;IETF standards already provide mechanisms to protect Internet communications and there are guidelines [&lt;a href=&quot;https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3552&quot;&gt;RFC3552&lt;/a&gt;] for applying these in protocol design. But those standards generally do not address PM, the confidentiality of protocol metadata, countering trafficanalysis, or data minimisation. In all cases, there will remain some privacy-relevant information that is inevitably disclosed by protocols.  […]&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Those developing IETF specifications need to be able to describe how they have considered PM, and, if the attack is relevant to the work to be published, be able to justify related design decisions. This does not mean a new “pervasive monitoring considerations” section is needed in IETF documentation. It means that, if asked, there needs to be a good answer to the question “Is pervasive monitoring relevant to this work and if so, how has it been considered?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;context-and-discussion&quot;&gt;Context and Discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This IETF memo gives a technical definition of Pervasive Monitoring and unambiguously considers it an &lt;em&gt;attack&lt;/em&gt; on the privacy of the user, in the technical sense that the party carrying out the monitoring is recording or modifying a user’s communication in a way that subverts the user’s intent. Having acknowledged this threat, the IETF, as a standards development organisation, commits to give ensure that the development of standards takes the mitigation of Pervasive Monitoring into account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;source&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7258&quot;&gt;https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7258&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;see-also&quot;&gt;See also&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tag/mass-surveillance&quot;&gt;Mass Surveillance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="position" /><category term="privacy" /><category term="mass surveillance" /><summary type="html">Pervasive Monitoring (PM) is widespread (and often covert) surveillance through intrusive gathering of protocol artefacts, including application content, or protocol metadata such as headers. Active or passive wiretaps and traffic analysis, (e.g., correlation, timing or measuring packet sizes), or subverting the cryptographic keys used to secure protocols can also be used as part of pervasivemonitoring. PM is distinguished by being indiscriminate and very large scale, rather than by introducing new types of technical compromise. The IETF community’s technical assessment is that PM is an attack on the privacy of Internet users and organisations. The IETF community has expressed strong agreement that PM is an attack that needs to bemitigated where possible, via the design of protocols that make PM significantly more expensive or infeasible.[…] IETF standards already provide mechanisms to protect Internet communications and there are guidelines [RFC3552] for applying these in protocol design. But those standards generally do not address PM, the confidentiality of protocol metadata, countering trafficanalysis, or data minimisation. In all cases, there will remain some privacy-relevant information that is inevitably disclosed by protocols. […] Those developing IETF specifications need to be able to describe how they have considered PM, and, if the attack is relevant to the work to be published, be able to justify related design decisions. This does not mean a new “pervasive monitoring considerations” section is needed in IETF documentation. It means that, if asked, there needs to be a good answer to the question “Is pervasive monitoring relevant to this work and if so, how has it been considered?”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Snowden on “armoring the user”</title><link href="https://software-ethics-casebook.github.io//snowden-on-armoring-the-user" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Snowden on &quot;armoring the user&quot;" /><published>2018-04-06T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-04-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://software-ethics-casebook.github.io//snowden-on-armoring-the-user</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://software-ethics-casebook.github.io//snowden-on-armoring-the-user">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The lesson of 2013 is not that the NSA is evil. It’s that the path is dangerous. The network path is something that we need to help users get across safely. Our job, as technologists, our job as engineers, our job as anybody who cares about the internet in any way, who has any kind of personal or commercial involvement is literally to armor the user, to protect the user and to make that they can get from one end of the path to the other safely without interference.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Now, one of the primary vulnerabilities of users around the world in terms of their relationship to great powers, whether that’s the national government, whether that’s foreign government, whether that’s groups that don’t like them very much, the fact that they can be de-anonymized for their thoughts and then some discriminatory action applied against them is very dangerous. I mean it’s a direct threat to their safety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;context-and-discussion&quot;&gt;Context and Discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edward Snowden made this statement during the opening remarks of a Q&amp;amp;A session with him at an IETF meeting in Prague (following a screening of the documentary CITIZENFOUR about the NSA spying scandal.) He echoes &lt;a href=&quot;an-open-letter-from-us-researchers-in-cryptography-and-information-security&quot;&gt;IETF RFC 7258&lt;/a&gt; (which considered the mitigation Pervasive Monitoring an Internet Best Practice), and details his belief that, given that monitoring is largely inevitable, the privacy of users is best protected if software developers &lt;em&gt;themselves&lt;/em&gt; take responsibility for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/snowden-meets-IETF.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Snowden meets IETF (screencap from linked video)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;Sources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/mnot/382aca0b23b6bf082116&quot;&gt;Transcript&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/0NvsUXBCeVA&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mnot.net/blog/2015/07/20/snowden_meets_the_ietf&quot;&gt;Mark Nottingham’s blog post &lt;em&gt;Snowden Meets the IETF&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20170528052824/https://www.mnot.net/blog/2015/07/20/snowden_meets_the_ietf&quot;&gt;archive&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;discussion&quot;&gt;Discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=10059308&quot;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;related-entries&quot;&gt;Related entries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/an-open-letter-from-us-researchers-in-cryptography-and-information-security&quot;&gt;IETF Considers “Mitigation of Pervasive Monitoring” an “Internet Best Current Practice”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="position" /><category term="mass surveillance" /><category term="privacy" /><summary type="html">The lesson of 2013 is not that the NSA is evil. It’s that the path is dangerous. The network path is something that we need to help users get across safely. Our job, as technologists, our job as engineers, our job as anybody who cares about the internet in any way, who has any kind of personal or commercial involvement is literally to armor the user, to protect the user and to make that they can get from one end of the path to the other safely without interference. Now, one of the primary vulnerabilities of users around the world in terms of their relationship to great powers, whether that’s the national government, whether that’s foreign government, whether that’s groups that don’t like them very much, the fact that they can be de-anonymized for their thoughts and then some discriminatory action applied against them is very dangerous. I mean it’s a direct threat to their safety.</summary></entry></feed>